[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
well good evening everybody I'm glad to
see you back all of you so nice to have
such a large
class the last time we discussed the
influence of electric and magnetic
fields on on charged particles we know
what they do we know what electric and
magnetic fields do on charged particles
they push them around they pull them
they exert
forces in fact we
even wrote some equations let's write
down the basic equation the basic
equation is that the force on a Charged
particle f is equal to the electric
charge of the charged particle why is
that there that's there because if the
charged particle wasn't char charged if
it didn't have any charge there would be
no force on it and then that gets
multiplied by the electric
field let's just call it the electric
field plus something that depends on the
magnetic field and the thing that
depends on the magnetic field is the
cross product of the Velocity with the
magnetic
field that's the basic
influence
of electric and magnetic fields on
charged particles is to exert forces on
them to push them and pull them around
and so
forth the missing piece thus far is what
is it that determines the electric and
magnetic fields in
space what is it that determines whether
there's a electromagnetic wave what is
it that determines if a electric charge
produces an electric field and so forth
what are the equations which govern the
fields
themselves those equations are called
Maxwell's equations and those are the
equations we want to discuss this
evening they're the equations which tell
you how charged particles affect Fields
here is the equation which says how
Fields affect charged particles the
other half of the coin is how charged
particles affect Fields why is it
necessary that charged particles affect
Fields well it's a kind of action and
reaction thing if electric and magnetic
fields can influence particles what does
that mean it means an electromagnetic
wave can come hit a charge particle and
send it off flying off in some other
direction it can add energy to the
charged particle well if an electric
field can add energy to a Charged
particle then it had better be that a
Charged particle can suck energy out of
an electric field otherwise energy
wouldn't be conserved so it stands to
reason it's a kind of action and
reaction thing that if electric and
magnetic fields can do things to
particles charged particles then charged
particles charged currents electric
charges had better be able to do things
to electric and magnetic
fields so that's this topic for tonight
but as always in this course the basic
question is whether the laws of physics
and in this case the laws of the
electric and magnetic field are the same
in all reference frames that's the thing
we've been concentrating on in the study
of
Relativity is the idea that the basic
laws of physics are the same in all
reference frames now one of the things
we're going to write down Maxwell's
equations in a
moment but one of the basic things
that uh we
learned by well go back a step one of
the basic questions has to do with light
all of all of Relativity Theory had to
do with light if Maxwell's equations are
the theory of light and Maxwell's
equations tell you that light moves with
the speed of light and Maxwell equations
are the same in every reference frame it
stands to reason that light will move
with a speed of light in every reference
frame this was precisely the puzzle that
Einstein wrestled with so hard how is it
it possible to get a description of
nature in which light moves with the
same velocity in every frame of
reference
that the thing which ensures that is
that the laws of physics are the same in
every reference frame and in past
lectures we saw that what that meant is
that the equations of physics should be
expressed in terms of quantities which
have definite transformation laws when
you go from frame to frame that means
scalers that don't change it means
vectors for vectors it means tensors and
it means all the things that we
discussed last time when we discussed
the transformation properties of the
various things in
physics let me just remind you what this
equation looks like if it's expressed in
a covariant form in a form which is the
frame same in every reference
frame it
looks
like an
expression involving not electric and
magnetic fields well yes electric and
magnetic fields but a tensor a field
tensor and I'll remind you in a little
while what that field tensor is but it's
an anti-symmetric field tensor which is
built up out of the electric and
magnetic fields and it's multiplied by
the four Vector of
velocity this is
the Muth component of the force the Muth
component of the force is written in
terms of a
4x4 anti-symmetric tensor whose
transformation properties we know and
the four Vector of velocity in this
form the lorence force law is written in
a form which is manifestly the same in
every reference frame so that our goal
is to write all of the laws of physics
in particular the Maxwell equations
today in a FR in a form which is the
same in every reference frame which
means writing it in terms of vectors and
tensors and so
forth now let's just talk for a little
bit before we get into it deeply let's
talk about the kind of effects that
charges have on electric and magnetic
fields not that electric and magnetic
fields have on charges but that charges
have on electric and magnetic fields
well first of all we know that if we
have an electric charge we'll call an
electric charge
q q stands for the electric charge if we
have an electric charge of a certain
magnitude it creates around it an
electric field you've all seen pictures
of this the electric field spreads out
away from the charge very much like a
fluid emanating from a uh from a pipe
might spread out except it spreads out
in three dimensions that's the electric
field created by a point charge another
example is if we have an electric
current moving through a wire and
electric currents are nothing but moving
electric charges electric charges moving
through a wire those electric charges
their motion creates a magnetic field
and the magnetic
field is a field which circulates around
the wire like
that so these are examples of how
charges and currents create
Fields what happens for example if you
move the charge supposing I suddenly
move the charge from one point to
another point then the field has to
rearrange
itself instead of pointing out of this
point it will point out of this point
but it can't do that
instantly why not because somebody out
here is not allowed to see an effect
before light could have been transmitted
to this point so the field cannot
suddenly rearrange when you move a
charge it rearranges by spreading out a
wave by spreading out a wave of
rearrangement so that a little bit after
the charge has been moved nearby the
charge the field is been rearranged but
far away it's just as it was before and
then as time goes on a wave spreads out
away from the
charge that signals the field far away
to rearrange to accommodate the fact
that the charge has moved if you move
the charge back and
forth what will spread out is an
electromagnetic wave if you vibrate the
charge back and
forth then what you will see going out
is an electric and magnetic wave that
spreads out just like a light wave in
fact
that's what an antenna does an antenna
simply moves charge back and forth like
that the same thing is true of currents
and
wires if you suddenly reversed the
current in a wire you would reverse the
sign of the magnetic field instead of
the magnetic field circulating around
this way the magnetic field would
circulate around in the other direction
but that signal can't get very far in
Too Short a Time Einstein's rule was no
signal ever gets faster than the speed
of light so it takes some
time for somebody far away to discover
that the current has been reversed that
means that the magnetic we the change in
the magnetic field the fact that it's
changeed Direction spreads out in a wave
and again that's an electromagnetic wave
and if you oscillate the charge back and
forth if you oscillate the current back
and forth you send out an
electromagnetic wave that's the basic
physics that we want to describe
by Maxwell's
equations before we
do I want to do a little bit of review
from last
time first I just want to remind you
about wave equations equations
describing
fields and in this case Des describing
fields that can produce
waves the first example and we talked
about it last time was a scalar field
a field that doesn't have any indices mu
and new but is just a single number at
each point in space each point in space
there's a
quantity the field fi it depends on x
and
t and it can vibrate it can shake it can
do all sorts of things it can form wave
Fields the last time we discussed the
kind of equation the kind of wave
equation that governs in such fields and
I'll just remind
you remember what D mu is D mu stands
for the derivative with respect to the
four directions of SpaceTime x and
t mu runs over four
values x y z and T incidentally remember
that X here really stands for X Y and Z
perhaps I shouldn't call it X call it X
well let's let's continue to call it X
but it really stands for the four
components of space and also T stands
for the time D byd mu means the
derivative with respect to any one of
these so that's uh that's an ordinary
derivative and we can differentiate f a
simple wave equation a very simple wave
equation would just say that the
derivative of the field is zero
that's not a very interesting wave
equation and the reason is what it says
is the field is absolutely constant if
all of its derivatives the X and the Y
and the Z and the time derivative are
zero that means the field doesn't change
at all with anything and so that's a
very boring wave equation completely
boring a less boring equation we get if
we differentiate it
again
I'm now using notation that we described
last time or several times in the past
where an upper index and a lower
index differ only by the sign of the
time
component so that this would really
mean the second derivative with respect
to
time of the field minus the second
derivative with respect to
x^2 minus the second derivative with
respect to
y^2 minus the second derivative with
z^2 is equal to zero notice as usual
because I'm lazy I've set the speed of
light c equal to
one you can go home and as an exercise
figure out where the speeds of light go
into this equation all right let's
imagine now a a wave moving down the
z-axis a wave moving down the z-axis
it's moving down the z-axis and that
means F only depends on Z it doesn't
depend on X and Y it may also depend on
time if a wave is moving and you're
standing still watching it of course
you're going to watch it go up and down
and up and down so it will depend on
time and it will also depend on Z where
you are but it won't depend on the other
directions so a wave moving down the
z-axis we can completely ignore these
two terms which are the derivatives of
fi in the direction in which it doesn't
change so this is not
there and our wave equation for a wave
moving along Z along the z- axis sorry
this should be Z shouldn't
it should equal
zero what kind of solutions does such an
equation can have we talked about it
last time and there are two basic
solutions that this equation has one of
them is a
function of z+
T and the other is a function of Z minus
t these are the two solutions which
represent waves moving to the right
along the z-axis and waves moving to the
left this one represents waves moving to
to the right along the positive z-axis
this one represents waves moving along
the to the left what function any
function any function any shaped wave
profile take any shaped wave profile at
all and allow it to just move uniformly
along the Z direction that constitutes a
wave moving down the z- axis along the
positive Z Direction that's a function
of Z minus t if the wave moves in the
other direction then the same it's the
same function of z+ T so that's the
basic facts that we learned last time
about
waves and there's one particular special
kind of
wave the s or cosine wave let's just
write it down for future
reference a wave which really has a wavy
look to it like
this well you can guess that's either a
sign or a
cosine and so for example a wave of this
type moving off to the right would be a
solution of the wave equation which has
the form
cosine of Z minus t z minus t because
it's moving to the right and furthermore
you can throw in a constant here usually
called K the wave number any constant
the bigger the constant is incidentally
the shorter the wavelength of the wave
so if K is Big the wave looks like this
if K is small the wave looks like
this those are the basic facts that I
want you to remember about wave
equations uh and in particular wave
solutions that they have functions of Z
minus t z+ t they can have different
wavelengths and they can be signs
cosiness they move to the right or they
move to the left that's it that's what
we need to know about
waves before we go ahead with Maxwell's
equations just to remind you just to uh
since it's been a week since we went
through this I will remind you of a
little bit of
mathematics elementary
mathematics first of all is the notion
of the cross product of two vectors if
we have any two vectors these are
ordinary vectors not four vectors now
ordinary three-dimensional vectors in
three-dimensional space then we have the
cross product b.
a b cross a excuse me the cross product
of two vectors the cross product is
itself another Vector if we have two
vectors each pointing in some Direction
with a given
length we can multiply them together
and make another
Vector the cross product is defined by
its components so for example the X
component of b cross a is defined this
is
definition is defined to be b y * a x -
BX * a
y and now if you want to find the other
components you just cycle through x y
and z B so for example B cross a the Y
component you go X to y equals B well y
goes to
Z x goes to Y the root is X to y y to Z
Z back to X B goes to Z sorry y goes to
Z x goes to Y minus b y x goes to y a
goes to Z and likewise for the last I'm
doing this once I won't do it again B
cross
a z component of it is equal to X Y the
next uh y z the next one must be X BX X
Y the next one must be
Z minus
bz ax these are
definitions these are definitions of the
cross product between two vectors notice
that the cross product itself has
components and so it must be a vector
okay now another way of multiplying two
vectors together is the dot product the
dot
product the dot product of two
vectors is a
scalar a do B and it only has one
component it's the same in every
reference frame or same when you rotate
the reference frame
and its definition is ax
BX plus a y by
y plus a z bz can that be read I hope
that can be read ax BX plus a y b y plus
a z bz that's the dot product and it's a
scalar that's one set of Concepts that
uh that we've been through several
times now the other set of
concepts are the curl of a vector and
the Divergence of a
vector and here's the way you think
about them they're built up out of
derivatives of the components of the
vector partial derivatives with respect
to X Y and Z all you have to imagine in
your head is that derivative with
respect to X and derivative with respect
to Y and derivative with respect to Z PR
pretend that those symbols are the three
components of a vector they're not
they're the three components of a
derivative but just pretend that they're
the three components of a vector and now
imagine Dell cross a vector a what does
that mean it's something that's made up
out of the derivatives of the components
of
a but oh I'm sorry the uh the three
components are called called the vector
Dell Dell is just a short hand for
upside down
triangle Dell cross a how do you make it
well you just go back to this formula
and wherever you saw a stick in either d
by DX d by Dy or D by DZ so the curl of
a is then just given by well we have a
so that's d by
DX I should have called this B shouldn't
I it would have made more sense and been
nicer if I would have called this
B all right so instead of a we write the
three components of the derivative
wherever we see B we just stick B so
that's
BX
slow we're doing the curl the curl is
over here the X component of the curl D
crossb the X component of it all right
that's
this all
right so it's ax by y well that's d by
DX b
y minus d by Dy y
BX we can go through it and cycle
through it and find the other components
of the of the curl of B but they're
always made up D by Dy d by Dy they're
always made up of derivatives of the
components of B in the same pattern in
the same exact pattern that the cross
product is made up what about Del do B
that's called the Divergence of B Del do
B well we come to the definition of the
diver convergence of the dot product ax
* BX that will be D by
DX
BX plus d by
Dy b y plus d by d
z
bz now these two objects they're
composed out of derivatives of the
components of vectors if a vector is
constant in space if it's a vector field
which is constant in space it has
neither neither a Divergence nor a
curl roughly speaking a vector has a
Divergence when it seems to be emate a
vector field has a Divergence when it
seems to be emanating out of someplace
like
this a vector has a curl when it seems
to curl around
someplace so if we had a magnetic field
for example in a wire that was going
into the
Blackboard that Vector would have a
curl if we have an electric
charge giving rise to an electric field
pointing out from some point that field
would have a
Divergence we've gone through these
things before these are not new just
reminding you of
them and now I want to write down
Maxwell's equations in terms of these
objects our goal is going to be to write
Maxwell's equations that's easy you can
get them off somebody's t-shirt lots and
lots of t-shirts with Maxwell's
equations on
them but then to understand in what
sense they are the same in every
reference frame that's our goal to see
that Maxwell's equations can be written
in a form which is the same in every
reference
frame all right so let me write them
down
curl of the electric
field the electric field you construct
its
curl is equal to
minus the time derivative of the
magnetic
field that's Maxwell equation number
one Maxwell equation number
two Divergence of the magnetic field is
equal to
zero all that says
is that the magnetic
field doesn't have any sources in the
same sense that the electric field does
it doesn't emanate out from a point it
tends to wind around
things okay the next
equation is an equation similar to this
but it involves Del Cross of the
magnetic field and it's equal to plus d
by DT
so these two equations look very similar
it's almost as though you interchanged
electric and magnetic field but not
quite there's a sign difference between
them if you just interchange the
magnetic and electric field you get the
wrong sign here and the last one is just
del. eal
Z in quite parallel with uh the magnetic
field here these are the basic Maxwells
equations but these are the Maxwells
equations when there are no charges
around in the absence of charges in
currents let me put back in what happens
when there are charges in currents in
other words these are the equations that
call the Mac the uh the vacuum Maxwell
equations they describe electric and
magnetic fields in completely empty
space with no electric charges no
currents let me just tell you now what
happens if you add
in some electric charges some electric
currents and so forth they do have an
effect on uh on things and so for
example I'm going to write in a red
here the actual thing that goes the
charge density the charge density is
called row and it's the amount of
electric charge per unit
volume at every point in space there may
or may not be some charge in every
little cell of space there may be some
charge the charge per unit volume is
called the charge density so what really
goes here is the charge
density but if there is no charge
density well then it just isn't there
over here there's another term and it's
the electric current it's called J and
I'll Define it for you
later but for the moment I want to study
the Maxwell equ equations without
electric current and charges we want to
see if we can understand why those
equations are the same in every
reference
frame how can that possibly be why is it
a puzzle it's a puzzle because as we're
going to see these equations describe
light waves moving always with the same
speed they always move with the same
speed the speed of light they move down
the axis with the speed of light how can
they possibly be the same in every
reference
frame after all if I was a reference if
I was a reference frame moving down
following the wave I would expect to see
it moving
slower nevertheless these are equations
are the same in every reference frame
and in every reference frame they say
the speed of light is exactly the same
so let's see if we can recast these four
equations in a form which is the same in
every reference frame we have the tools
to do it well we have to remember
is that the electric and magnetic fields
combine together we did this last time
combine together into a tensor into an
anti- symmetric tensor so let's remind
ourselves of
that there an anti- symmetric tensor F
muu and it's made up it's 4x4 it's a
matrix and its components are made up
out of the electric and magnetic field
since it's anti- symmetric it has zeros
on the
diagonal incidentally in the first row
in the First Column I'm going to put the
time component the time component the X
Y and Z
components right let's we don't need
this
here all right so let me just fill it in
for you minus the X component of the
electric field
minus the Y component of the electric
field and minus the Z component of the
electric field and down here we have
plus e
subx plus e suby and plus e
subz an anti-symmetric Matrix always has
the property that what's above the
diagonal here is the negative of what's
below the
diagonal all right now what about in
these missing slots over here that's
where the magnetic fields go right over
here you have minus b
subz b
suby and minus B
subx and then down here you just
have uh the
reflected plus B
subz minus B
suby and plus b
subx
this is the electromagnetic field
tensor it transforms under Lorent
Transformations as a anti- symmetric
tensor I showed you how to do that last
time and uh there's nothing new about
it for the
moment Let's see we would call this
component over here the TX component the
first row here refers to
time the second row well the first row
is time the second row is X the third
row is y the fourth row is z and
likewise for the columns we would call
this e or we would call this F this
element over
here would be mu = T new =
X okay so as Mu and new both run over
XYZ and T we fill out this Matrix that's
the notion of the electromagnetic field
tensor and as I said it transforms in
the right way to be a
tensor there is another tensor that you
can make up out of the electromagnetic
field it is also a tensor and it is made
up by simply replacing electric field by
magnetic field and magnetic field by
electric field we just look at these
equations and we see that the electric
field and magnetic field occur almost
symmetrically it might not be a great
surprise that there's another tensor
which is made up of exactly I won't
write equal but another
tensor it's usually called f with a
little twiddle on top of it and all it
is is it's the same object except with
electric and magnetic fields
interchanged but not quite you don't
quite change electric to Magnetic and
magnetic to Electric you change electric
to magnetic but magnetic to minus
electric do I have that right no I don't
quite you replace
electric by minus
magnetic and magnetic by
Electric that's in order to account for
the sign difference here when you do
that you discover that there's another
tensor
quantity I'm not going to try to prove
for you that this transforms like a
tensor
it's just a uh straightforward
exercise and I not as young as I used to
be so I don't do as much exercise as I
used to on the Blackboard I won't do it
but we'll just write it down wherever
you see electric put minus magnetic
wherever you see magnetic put electric
so F twiddle the other electromagnetic
field tensor again zero on on the
diagonals
and
then
plus b
subx b
suby and b
subz and then wherever we see magnetic
we put back electric so minus
EZ
ey minus e
x and then on the other side here you
just have to remember that it's anti-
symmetric so everything on the
reflected side of the Matrix here is
just the opposite the negative of what
it is in the upper
half uh of the Matrix I won't bother
writing it
out these are two tensor quantities both
of which have the same transformation
properties and uh under Lorent
Transformations form a coherent set of
objects which are
tensor anti- symmetric
tensor if we can succeed in writing
Maxwell's equations here they are right
here if we can succeed in rewriting them
in terms of these objects in a way that
looks covariant which looks the same in
all reference frames then we will have
proved that these wave equations here
that these equations are the same in
every reference frame this is not hard
to do so let's see if we can guess the
answer
notice that Maxwell's equations each
have one derivative in them they don't
have second derivatives they have many
derivatives of course there's a
derivative with respect to T there's
derivatives with respect to X but they
never have higher derivatives they never
have second derivatives third
derivatives fourth derivatives and so
forth and so we
might try
to see if these equations here can be
Rewritten in terms of these field ATT
tensors
what can we write we have F mu
new that's electric and magnetic field
we can differentiate
it but what can we differentiate it with
respect to we can differentiate it of
course with respect to some
X but we want to make this equation
whatever it is we want to make it the
same in every reference frame and that
means we want to match indices covariant
and contravariant
indices you only about the only thing we
can write
down is this derivative with respect to
X mu of f mu new is equal to zero first
of all let's count how many equations
there are here let's count how many
equations there are there's one for each
new remember we sum over mu mu is a
summation
Index right so that's not a free index
in this problem there's one equation for
each new that means there are four
equations
those four equations we will see are
let's see they are these four equations
right
here why do I say there are four
equations here here's one and now there
are three components of this vector
equation this is a vector equation there
are three components ex x e y and e z
three components here one here those are
four
components let's check let's actually
check
that these four equations are what we
get from this it's not hard we just
write it
out first of all mu can be
t d by DT of f t
new Plus in fact let's uh
specialize let's take new to be
Z just for fun
let's take it to be Z and see what we
get d by DT of
ftz plus d by
DX of
fxz plus d by
Dy of
f y
z plus d by d
z of f
ZZ equals z
that's what this would
say if it's
true okay what about this
term derivative with respect to Z of fzz
fzz is zero because all of the diagonal
elements are
zero all right so we can forget this
this isn't
there fzz is
zero what is
fxz well to see what fxz is
we go to the X row and the Z column
that's b
y so let's just plug it in that's b
y what is
fyz for that we go to the
Y the Y row to the zth column and that's
minus B subx so that gives us
minus B
subx well that's looking good this is d
by DX of b y minus d by Dy of BX this
looks very much like a piece of the curl
of
B and that's what it is what about
ftz well we go to the T row to the Z's
place and we get
minus E
subz so this is
minus the derivative of e
subz with respect to
T all of that equals
zero well if you look at it carefully
you'll see that it's exactly the
equation over here the Z component of it
the time derivative of e
subz is the Z component of the curl of B
that's exactly what we have here so we
check
that the uh let's see which component
was that that was the Z component over
here the Z component just gives us back
one of the Maxwell equations namely the
Z component of a Maxwell equation the
only other case which is interesting is
to write down the time component here or
the T component t for time
uh well let's let's continue to call it
m
no let's work out
the time component of this
equation what does this read now first
of all it has a term which is d by
DT of
ftt that's mu equals T but that's
zero
ftt that's right here that's zero
so that's
zero and then we have what else d by
DX of
fxt plus d by
Dy of
fyt plus d by d
z of f
ZT what is FF what is fxt YT and ZT
those are just the components of the
electric field
fxt minus with a minus sign is e subx
the other one is e sub y and the other
one is e subz so all this says when
packaged neatly is that the derivative
with respect to X of e ex plus the
derivative with respect to Y of e y plus
the derivative with respect to Z of
EZ is equal to
zero that my friends is just d. E equals
0 for the moment we've been ignoring
charges and current
density charges and
currents so you can see that
um
that two of the Ma sorry four of the
Maxell equations four of the eight
Maxwell
equations just have the
form of a relativistically covariant
same in every reference
frame vector
equation it's a vector equation because
the left hand side is a vector it's a
vector because it is the derivative
where you have contracted the index mu
there's only one index left over and so
this is a vector equation it's the same
in every reference frame the point is
that if you went through the entire
labor
of doing the Lorent Transformations on
the coordinates and on the components of
e and B you would find out that after
the Loren transformation the equation
was exactly the
same okay what about the other half of
the Maxwell equations well those have
exactly the same
form
except with twiddle here
here of course they have exactly the
same form F twiddle is the same as F
except with e and B
interchanged and an extra minus sign
thrown in well that's just exactly
what's here if you go from here to Here
by interchanging electric and magnetic
fields with an extra sign here equations
are the
same so this this is a um a powerful way
to rewrite Maxwell's
equations again without charges without
current
densities this is a powerful way to
rewrite them in a simple and elegant
form but it's not the Simplicity and
elegance which is important it's the
recognition that these are four Vector
equations and therefore the same in
every reference
frame so Maxwell's equations then are
relativistically invariant they don't
change from frame to
frame we'll put back charges and
currents in a little
while but or maybe next time well I
think we'll do it this time but
um now that we've found that Maxwell's
equations are the same in every
reference frame what do they say what
are the
implications of these eight equations
what kind kind of electromagnetic fields
do they allow what do they describe so
let's again forget currents and
densities for the
moment
zero nothing there and let's study these
four they're not four equations they're
eight
equations let's study them and see if we
can make wave equations out of them now
if we go back I don't know what we did
with the wave equation we had it
someplace here
there it
is the wave equation is an equation with
second
derivatives second derivatives mean you
differentiate
twice okay Maxwell's equations all have
only first
derivatives but they have two distinct
Fields e and B we're going to find out
that having these are called first order
equations because they only have first
derivatives but we have first first
order derivatives first order equations
for e and first order equations for B
two variables we're going to find out
that that's equivalent to having second
order equations for either the electric
field or the magnetic field separately
this is not hard to do this is easy to
do so we need let's see we'll need a
clear Blackboard over here and we'll
need to manipulate this a little
bit I have e and B all mixed up but I
want to write an equation just for the
electric field I want to try to isolate
just the electric field and see how it
behaves so here's what I
do let's
see take this equation over here and
let's differentiate it with respect to
time it's got only one time derivative
in it let's differentiate it again with
respect to time so that we get a second
time
derivative then it will be DC e by dt^ 2
second derivative of the electric field
and that's going to equal D
cross the time derivative of
B if I differentiate with respect to
time over here I just get the second
time derivative of the electric field if
I differentiate with respect to T over
here that just differentiates the
magnetic field with respect to time okay
that hasn't helped yet I still have the
electric and the magnetic field in the
same equation the goal was to get rid of
the magnetic field but look right here I
have the magnetic field or its time
derivative written in terms of the
electric field so I can be clever and
simply get rid of dbdt here and call it
curl of e minus the curl of e so let's
just let's first it was what was it it
was um
Del cross
dbdt and now for the BDT we substitute
minus curl of e so that gives us a minus
sign and a curl of
e here we have an equation which only
involves the electric field second
derivative with respect to T on the left
hand side and various complicated
derivatives on the right hand side what
I'm going to do is I'm going to take the
X component of this equation both sides
of the equations are
vectors e is a vector differentiating it
with respect to time leaves it a vector
and the cross product or the curl of a
curl is also a vector so let's take the
X component of both sides the X
component of both
sides what we have to
calculate
is the X component of the curl of the
curl that's a slightly tedious operation
if you like you can go to sleep for two
minutes until I get the answer but I
will do it on the Blackboard for
you okay Dell cross D cross e the X
component what we have to know is that
the X component of a
curl the X component of a curl
is equal to the derivative of the Z
component with respect to Y minus the
derivative of the Y component with
respect to
Z all right we are taking the X
component of Del cross a of Del
cross a that's this all right so now we
want the X component of D cross Del
cross
e
that means I just substitute for a
wherever I see a I substitute Del cross
e so let's see what's that going to give
me that's going to give me D by
Dy of a z which should be Del cross e z
component of it minus d by d
z of Del cross
e the Y component of it but now we
substitute for these components the same
trick the same trick and here is the re
result the grand result it's D by
Dy
with derivative of e with respect to x
minus derivative of e x with respect to
y That's d by Dy of this term
and then there are two more plus d by
DZ of the e
x by
DZ minus
DZ by
DX and
then I think that's
it that's it two
terms okay okay wake up now the worst is
over let's see what we have we're
calculating the X component of a vector
we're calculating the X component of a
vector let's see what we have here we
first of all have second derivatives of
EX with respect to Y let's see what we
have first of all d by dy^ 2 of
EX that's this term let me cross them
out as we pick them
off that's
this D by dy^ 2 two derivatives with
respect to Y of EX we have two
derivatives with respect to Z of
EX plus second derivative with respect
to z^2 of
EX that's
this and then we get two other
terms which look a little mysterious
what are they they are
derivative with respect to X of
dyy that's this term over
here it looks a little different because
I've interchanged the X and Y
derivative all right it was derivative
with respect to X followed by derivative
with respect to Y you're allowed to
Interchange those so the first term here
is d by DX of d y y and then there's
another term which is d by
DX of I think it's DZ
EZ neither one of these the top one or
the bottom one looks very
elegant but if I add a term to the
top and subtract the same term From The
Bottom the whole thing will have a nice
form so let's add
plus d by dx2 e
x and let's now
subtract d by
DX of d by
DX E
X I have added and subtracted exactly
the same thing now you should be able to
see a
pattern first of all we have Dy ey y
plus DZ EZ this should be a I think
I overall sign mistake
yeah Dy y DZ EZ and DX X appear inside
here what is that that's just d. e but
d. e is equal to zero that's one of
Maxwell's equations and so all of this
DX X Plus Dy e y plus DZ EZ Z is just
zero not there at
all what about this term this is nice
the second derivative with respect to
y^2 x^2 and z^2 of the same quantity e
subx let's put it together now let's put
it together what was it here's what we
were doing the second derivative with
respect to X of
t^2 is minus
D cross D cross e the X component of it
and that's exactly what we computed over
here that long tedious computation just
give us a leftand side let's erase it
and let's replace it by what we
computed and you'll see a
pattern it is d by dx^ 2 e x X plus d by
D y^ 2 E X plus d by dz^2
e
x if you've kept track which you
probably have not of the original wave
equation you'll see that this is just a
wave equation for the component
ex ex is a field which satisfies just
the same old wave equation that we wrote
down for five if you remember we wrote
down a wave equation for fi it had
exactly the same
form and so e the E the electric field
itself satisfies a wave equation a good
old wave equation the same wave equation
which had Right Moving and left Moving
Solutions which could be signs and
cosiness what have we
learned we've learned that there are
waves of electric field that can
propagate we've learned that the wave
equation which gives rise to propagating
waves that can move to the left or right
applies or any other direction of course
but which applies to
um uh to the Scala field also applies
directly to the components of the
electric
field all right let's see whether we can
build ourselves an electric wave an
electromagnetic wave
wave this
equation has
Solutions of the
form for example
e is equal to
cosine of let's just take a simple
example Z minus t this would be a wave
moving down the
axis it's a wave equation it has a
solution which is a wave moving down the
z-axis
all right that's what this cosine Z
minus t is I could put a constant K but
let's leave it out it only complicates
things this would be a wave whose
electric field is pointed along the
x-axis let's draw some coordinates
here's
Z here's X and here's y sticking out of
the
Blackboard this is a wave moving down
z-axis its electric field is along the
xaxis for Simplicity let's take it not
to have any component along the Y AIS
and it looks like a
cosine so it's an electric
field points up points down points up
points
down and it propagates needless to say
with the speed of light why the speed of
light we've worked in units in which the
speed of light is
one and the this is just a wave moving
down the z-axis with unit
velocity Z proportional to T the whole
thing just makes an Excursion down the
z-axis without changing shape all right
that's the electric field and I've
chosen it arbitrarily to point in the X
Direction incidentally a wave an
electromagnetic wave where the electric
field points along the X direction is
called a polarizer wave polarized along
the x-axis this is polarized light
polarized light polarized along the
x-axis okay what about the magnetic
field can the magnetic field be any oh
wait before we do that let's do we've
decided arbitrarily somewhat to set the
Y component equal to zero let's just do
that we could have put a y component in
also but I decided just to keep it
simple what about the Z component of the
uh uh of the electric field let me prove
to you that that has to be zero it has
to be zero because d. e is equal to Z
what is d. e it's the derivative of the
X component with respect to X but the X
component doesn't depend on
X plus the derivative of the Y component
with respect to y
also doesn't depend on
y plus the derivative of the Z component
with respect to
Z these two terms in the Divergence of
the electric field vanish so must this
one so what that says is that the
derivative of ez with respect to Z must
be equal to zero in other words the Z
component of the magnetic field of the
electric field cannot vary As you move
along here it must be constant
constant could be a constant electric
field let's just throw it away a
constant electric field is not very
interesting it's certainly not part of a
wave
motion we could get rid of it by putting
it between capacitor plates and
canceling the uniform electric field the
point is that the wave part of the field
the part that varies as you go down the
z-axis must not be there for the Z
component so only the X component of the
electric field is there the Y component
and the Z component are just not there
zero what does that mean about the
magnetic
field well we
can use this equation over here to tell
us the something about the magnetic
field what first of all what about the
curl of the electric field the curl of
the electric field what components does
the curl of the electric field have well
the only components that it can have
would have to come from something like
deex by
DZ that's the kind of thing that appears
in the curl of the electric field well
we would also have minus
DZ by
DX this would be the Y component of the
curl but Z is the Z component isn't
there we've already established that so
that's not there so for example this
would be the Y component of the M of the
uh of the curl of the electric field
it's there if you differentiate ex with
respect to Z you'll get an
answer you will get an answer so there
is a y component to the curl of
E
and that's all there is no other
component to the curl of e except for
the Y
component uh we could look for some
other component let's look for the Z
component that would be DX by
y minus Dy the
E by X well ex doesn't depend on y and e
y is zero allog together there's no
other component so the only
component of the curl of E
is along the Y
AIS the electric field is along the
xais is's the z-axis and the magnetic
field is along the Y AIS why is the
magnetic field along the y- axis because
its time derivative is along the y axis
if the time derivative is along the Y
AIS the field itself must be along the Y
AIS
so we see then that the magnetic field
let's draw the magnetic field in
green lies
perpendicular see if we can draw
it here's the magnetic
field here's the electric
field electric and magnetic field are
perpendicular to each other and they're
also perp pendicular to the motion of
the wave that's what follows from these
equations the whole set of equations has
wav like Solutions with the electric and
magnetic field both oscillating they're
both going up and down except the
magnetic field is going left and right
and the whole thing is pro proceeding
down the
z-axis that's the nature of
electromagnetic waves electric and
magnetic fields perpendicular to the
direction of motion all moving uniform L
down the axxis with a speed of
light what's more you can be sure that
if you were to take this electromagnetic
wave and look at it from another frame
of reference it would have exactly the
same properties why because the Maxwell
equations are the same in every
reference frame so the properties of
electromagnetic waves will be the same
in every reference frame and they'll
always have this property of moving with
a speed of light and having Electric
cross electric and magnetic fields
perpendicular to each other and to the
direction of
motion that's the character of light and
all other electromagnetic
radiation all right now let's let's um
put
back the things we took out
namely let's ask what happens when we
have charges and currents in Maxwell's
equations how do we describe it how do
we describe it and what does it do most
important is it lorensen variant in
other words is it the same in every
reference frame that is our major goal
to show that the laws of
electromagnetism are the same in every
reference frame so what do we have to do
uh I'll just remind
you that the two Maxwell equations on
the right hand side strictly speaking
the four Maxwell equations on the right
hand side get modified they get Modified
by
putting a charge density and I will
explain what that means on the right
hand side over here
plus a current
density the current is the current of
electric charge so let me explain what
those things mean the charge density
which is called row this is the symbol
row I don't know why charge density has
always had the symbol row associated
with it nor do I know why the current
has the symbol J associated with it but
it goes way back uh I think it goes back
to Faraday but if not it goes back
further than me
anyway Row the charge density is defined
in the following way imagine you have
lots and lots and lots of electrons and
they could be other kinds of charge
particles protons even some neutral
particles it doesn't matter but uh that
space is filled with a lot of particles
so many of
them charges of different kinds that uh
that you're tempted to think of it as a
continuous distribution of charge the
charge just like water is a bunch of
molecules but when you look at more
water in a CO grained way you think
about water as being a nice continuous
distribution of stuff okay now you take
a little volume of
space a little volume of space let's
call it volume v make it a small volume
we're going to think calculus we're
going to think differentially a small
volume of
space it's called a DV and take the
charge in that small volume of space if
the volume of the space is very small
and shrunk to smaller and smaller
dimensions of course the charge will
also shrink the smaller and smaller
Dimensions but the ratio let's call the
amount of charge in there let's call it
DQ a small charge in a small volume and
the ratio of the amount of charge per
unit volume is called the
density okay so it's the charge per unit
volume except that each point of space
evaluated separately so it could vary
from place to place you can have regions
with heavy charge density regions with
light charge density
and in calculating this you add up the
plus charges you subtract off the minus
charges all the obvious things add the
add the protons subtract the
electrons and get a net charge density
in each region of space and that charge
density is itself a function of position
but it could also depend on time how
could it depend on time well for example
charges could move from one place to
another this whole pile of charge could
move over to here in which case if we
stood at a particular point the charge
density would change it would change
from something to nothing so the charge
density also depends on the
time okay now it can't depend in any old
way there is a rule in nature and it's
called the conservation of charge the
total amount of charge in the world must
not change
right so how much what is the total
amount of charge in the whole world you
add up all of the charges in each little
cell of
space you add it all up and that becomes
an integral the total charge let's call
it capital Q total charge in the world
is the
integral over all of volume of space of
the charge
density
little DV here that just means you add
up all of the cells in each cell there's
a charge which is equal to DQ which is
row *
DV so you add up all the row times DVS
that's what an integral is it just means
add them all up and that gives you the
total charge in this case in the whole
world we could also for example just
talk about the charge in a region of
space space we could pick a particular
region of space with well defined
boundaries this
room or some other particular region of
space and talk about the charge in that
in that uh region in which case this
integral wouldn't go over all space it
would just go over the selected region
in this case for example the room and
that would be the charge inside the
room now charge is not allowed to just
change something some place and reappear
someplace
else it's not allowed according to the
laws of physics for reasons that'll
become more or less clear in a second to
suddenly disappear over here and
reappear over here well let's go back a
step first of all the rule of
Nature and it's an empirical law of
nature the empirical law of nature is
that the total amount of charge in the
universe never
changes okay that's called conservation
of electric
charge but the rule is stronger than
that for example you could have a
situation where charge on the earth
disappears and instantly with nothing
happening in between the same charge
appears on
Mars that would satisfy the rules of the
conservation of charge that the amount
of charge doesn't change what was lost
on Earth reappeared with Mar on
Mars and the conservation of charge does
not tell you that something has to
happen in between but that's forbidden
that's not the way charges change and
that's not the way charges move they
can't disappear over here and reappear
over here unless there's a flow of
charge in
between in other words if charge
disappears over here and reappears over
here somebody in between had better be
seeing a current flow between
them how do we express this idea that
charges don't just appear and disappear
and in fact they don't uh they don't
move from one place to another except by
virtue of a current of electric charge
flowing from one place to another so for
that we have to invent the idea of a
current so let me explain what a current
is it's a simple
idea let's uh let's put this
upstairs
bring this
downstairs let's take a little area in
space there's a little area in
space uh I'm going to redraw
it a little area a small area an
infinitesimally small
area we it's it's normally called D
Sigma D indicating that it's small
differential and sigma standing for
surface
area Okay so the amount of surface area
is called D Sigma but when people write
D Sigma they mean something a little
more they mean a vector now how the hell
can an area be a vector well what you do
is you take that area and you assign to
it a vector perpendicular to the area to
the area
element we'll decide in a few minutes
which direction do I do it to the left
or do I do it to the right but for the
moment just imagine assigning to every
little element of area a vector whose
length whose magnitude is the little
area and whose direction is
perpendicular to the direction of area
that's called the surface element uh
Vector the surface element Vector the
sigma I could put a little Vector symbol
above it but uh we don't need it just
the
sigma now we can ask how much
charge flows through that area in a unit
of
time right how much charge flows through
that area per unit time or better yet we
can ask how much charge per time per
unit area flows through there the charge
flowing through there will certainly be
proportional to the area if the area is
Tiny a small amount amount of charge
will be able to flow through it for a
given situation if the area is made
large a larger amount of charge can be
flowing through
it the charge per unit area per
unit uh per
unit time charge per unit area let's
let's let's write the words
charge per
unit
area per unit time
through a little surface element is
called the
current now the current is a vector the
current is a vector you can see why that
should be so current is kind of
like
flow all right think of it as a flow of
all the electrons and protons uh flowing
through space at any point the flow has
a
Direction namely the direction that the
charges are flowing in and it also has a
magnitude and the magnitude is the
charge per unit area per unit uh per
unit time flowing through that area
that's the definition of the Char of the
of the current and as I said it is a
vector if I want to know the amount of
charge per unit time flowing through the
surface element then what I do is I take
the dot product of the surface element
with the current both of them being
vectors if for example the current is
Flowing parallel to the
surface that means the current is
perpendicular to D Sigma then this
product is zero so if the current flows
perpend the current flows along the
surface no current flows from one side
to the other okay if the current is
Flowing
perpendicular to the surface that means
it's parallel to D Sigma then you get
the full maximum brunt of the flow
through the uh through the surface
element that's why it's the dot product
the dot product measures the component
of one vector in the direction of the
other so this measures the component of
the flow in the direction perpendicular
to the surface element and it is not the
charge per unit area per unit time
but just the charge per unit time this
is the charge per unit
time
charge per unit
through the surface element D
Sigma so now you have the idea of the
flow of charge and the um sometimes
called the flu of charge flow or flux of
charge and current or electric current
are all the same thing okay notice we're
not necessarily talking about a current
through a wire a current through a wire
is a special case and if we opened up
the wire and made it a little bit big we
could put little surface elements of
area in there and see that the current
through a wire is made up out of exactly
these kind of currents fluxes of charge
Through the Wire but that's a special
case we can have currents flowing
through space currents currents flowing
along sheets or just currents flowing
along three-dimensional space and that's
the definition of
j okay now
let's concentrate on the following
question here we have a region of
space it has some charge in it and the
charge in it is the integral over the
volume
of the charge density
if there are currents flowing there may
be currents flowing into or out of the
region let's choose let's choose to make
up the boundary of the region out of a
whole bunch of little surface
elements right so the boundary is made
up I don't mean I mean the boundary if
we thought of this as a
balloon then the rubber of the balloon
we would make up out of a lot lot of
little surface elements here and now
let's by definition Point their little
dig sigmas out of the
balloon let's choose to make them out of
the
balloon supposing there's a knit current
flowing out of a balloon what does that
say about the charge inside the balloon
incidentally I'm not Imagining the
balloon changing its size or anything
it's just a fixed region of
space if there's current flowing net
current flowing out of the surface then
the current on the inside must be
changing okay the only way that the
current can change on or the only way
the charge can change on the inside the
only way the charge can change on the
inside is by passing from the inside to
the outside so if the charges is
changing if the charge on the inside is
changing you can be certain that there
must be a flow of current through the B
boundary and that tells you that there
must be a
J in fact we can write down a simple
equation we can write down that the time
rate of change in of the charge inside
this
region DQ by
DT that's equal to the integral
DV of D Ro by
DT the time rate of change of the
electric El charge inside this region
must
equal the current that's passing out
through the boundary actually with the
opposite sign if current is passing out
through the boundary with a positive
sign then the charge must be decreasing
on the inside so it must have a minus
sign in this formula and What's the
total charge that passes out of this
region per unit
time the total charge passing out amount
of the region per unit time is just the
integral of the
current dotted into the surface element
we just add up all the currents passing
through each one of these surface
elements that's the integral
here and this is a theorem
now or if you like perhaps it's a law of
nature rather than a
theorem that the time rate of change of
the current on the inside is equal to
the flux of charge passing out through
the surface of the balloon and that's
given by the integral of a current
dotted into the
sigma okay now we need a true theorem a
mathematical theorem rather than a law
of Nature and the mathematical theorem
which we won't
prove it's called gauss's
law sorry it is not called gaus G's law
it is called Gus's
theorem look up Gus's theorem it's
sometimes called the Divergence
Theorem but I will tell you what it is
it's a
relationship between these are this is
called a surface integral it's an
integral of a vector quantity over a
surface over a bounding surface it can
be related to an integral over the
interior and here's the theorem called
gaus
theorem G
the it says that the
integral of any
Vector integrated over the
surface is equal now this is an integral
over the
surface let's call
surface
is equal to an integral over the
volume now if I had my class here I
would ask them what they goes in there
anybody
know no okay the Divergence of the
vector the Divergence of the vector
itself so it's a relationship between a
surface integral of a vector and the
integral over the volume of the uh of
the Divergence of the
vector uh it's not obvious I'm not going
to prove it it actually it doesn't take
very many lines to prove but let's
assume it if we assume it then we can
write the right hand side of this
equation as an integral over the
volume so it's an integral over the
volume another integral over the volume
of the Divergence of the
current it's the spreading out of the
current the spreading out of the current
you know what it's like it's almost like
this I I'll give you a picture of what
the Divergence of a vector is if you
thought of the vector as the flow Vector
of some
water perhaps uh um flow Vector of some
water right and supposing some water was
being pumped in at each point of space
some hidden little pipes that you can't
see are bringing water in from outside
and dumping it in the pipes end uh in
different places in space so the water
is diverging out away from the tips of
the
pipes and going out and filling up
space the Divergence of the water or the
Divergence of the flow of the water is
basically just the the water coming out
of these individual pipes and what this
theorem says is that the amount of water
that's coming out of these little pipes
that are ending at this point and
flowing
out where's that water going to go it
has to go out of the
surface it has to go out of the surface
and that's this expression here that it
diverges the integral over the
boundary uh of the
surface
flow is also equal to the integral over
the interior of the volume of the
Divergence of the vector so that's a
general theorem about vectors it doesn't
have anything particular to do with
electricity it doesn't have anything
particular to do with anything special
other than the mathematical properties
of
vectors all right so now we have a new
theorem that the integral over any
volume take any volume whatever the
integral over any volume of the time
rate of change of the density of charge
is the integral over the volume of the
Divergence of the
current if two integrals like this are
equal but they're equal not only for
some particular volume but they're true
it's true for every volume that you can
think
of then there's only only one way that
that can be true if for any region that
you can pick the integral over the
volume of one thing is equal to the
integral over the volume of another
thing the only way that that can be true
is for the things themselves to be
equal that again is a mathematical
theorem but it's more or less obvious
that if for any region the integral of
one quantity is equal to the integral of
another quantity the two quantities have
to be equal and we come to an
interesting conclusion about the
connection between charge density and
current it says that the derivative with
respect to time of the charge density
that's this plus I'm bringing everything
over to the left hand side the
Divergence of the current let's write
that out that's derivative with respect
to X of J subx plus derivative with
respect to y of J suby plus derivative
with respect to Z of J
subz equals
zero now if this is to be true in every
frame of reference and I didn't specify
anything particular about any particular
frame of reference when I told you this
little story if it's to be true in every
frame of reference it better have the
form of some invariant equation and it's
not hard to imagine how you make an
invariant equation out of this you first
of
all
say that the current well not first of
all you say that the current JX JY and
JZ together with row four quantities row
JX let me put the X upstairs now
JY
JZ form a four
vector they form the four Vector J
mu where mu goes from time and the three
components of
space that is what is suggested by
having these four components row JX JY
and JZ and
then this equation which is called the
continuity equation it's called the
continuity equation it takes the simple
form that D mu J mu is equal to zero
what does that say it says derivative
with respect to T of JT plus derivative
with respect to X of JX blah blah blah
is equal to zero which is exactly what
this
says so the way to make this continuity
equation be a equation that's true in
every frame of reference is to think of
the four components of current and
density as a four vector Vector that's
not too
surprising the current kind of
represents the velocity of the motion of
the charges as we've seen over and over
again the velocity Vector is a four
Vector the velocity Vector of an object
the relativistic velocity Vector of an
object is a four vector and so it's not
so surprising that the flow of a fluid
should also be described by a four
vector and the four Vector is the four
Vector of current and
density well okay now we have a object
the four Vector of current and velocity
that we can try to put into Maxwell's
equation
somehow let's go back to Maxwell's
equations which seem to have disappeared
off the Blackboard so I guess well let's
see if they have maybe they're
underneath here nah okay so let's write
Maxwell's equations again this time
putting in the charges and
currents okay here they
go d. e is equal to
row D.B is equal to
Zer D cross e is equal to minus DB by
DT these are all Vector equations and D
cross B is equal to d e by
DT plus
J where J is exactly the same J that I
defined here the current per unit area
per unit time okay what I assert and
which we'll check is that these
equations are exactly the same as the
following
equations D
mu F mu new remember what f muu is f muu
is a 4x4 anti- symmetric m a tensor
which is built up out of the electric
and magnetic field
components right that that is
equal to J
new notice the left hand side you've
contracted the MU index so the MU index
is not really a real index here it just
has one new index on the right hand a
new
index okay let's
check that this simple covariant
equation this is clearly a covariant
equation this is a tensor
differentiating a tensor gives you a
vector this is a vector and so uh this
equation would be invariant and the same
in every reference frame assuming that J
transforms as a vector so let's just
check that we get the same equation I'm
not going to do them uh let's see the
ones the ones that's relevant here are
the ones with the right hand side the
ones with
current
and charges density there are four
equations here for new for the four
different uh values of new there are
four equations here 1 2 3 4 so let's
check to see if any of them are the same
first of all let's take the time
component the time component would be D
mu F mu T is equal to JT but what is JT
that's the time component of
the of the four Vector of current
it's
row so on the right hand side we have
row and what about the leftand side to
see what the left hand side is we have
to go and rewrite the field tensor but
we don't need the whole thing all we
really need to remember is let's see
that um in
the uh that we have the components of
the electric field zero X ey Y and
EZ along
here we also have minus e x minus E Y
minus E Z and then we have the magnetic
field sitting in here in various
ways okay so let's see what we have we
have only the time components of F that
means the components along this first
row here we can write this as DX X
fxt Plus Dy
fyt plus
DZ
fzt am I missing one yes I missing one
I'm missing
DT
ftt but ftt is zero all the diagonal
elements of the Matrix are zero so this
is
zero now what is fxt fyt and fzt those
are the components of the electric field
so what is this this is just DX E X Plus
Dy e
y plus DZ
EZ in other words it is del.
e the left hand side is just dell. e and
the right hand side is
row we could go through the other
components in other words exactly the
same thing instead of taking the time
component here we could take space
component for example and set this equal
to
JX and we would
discover the X component of this
equation so the upshot of it is that the
connection between
charges and
Fields the way in which
charges charges and currents electric
charges electric currents the way they
generate Fields is lorensen variant it's
the same in all reference frames on the
other hand we've already seen that the
way that the fields influence the
charges as forces on them are also the
same in all reference frames so we see
that basically all of the equations of
electromagnetism can be written in a
form in which we can immediately check
that they're tensor equations and
therefore the same in every reference
frame that was the real goal of this to
show
that the laws of electromagnetism are
the same in every reference frame number
one and number two to demonstrate that
the laws of electromagnetism lead to
light waves moving with the speed of
light from those two things it follows
that light travels with the speed of
light in every frame of
reference and that sort of closes up and
finishes up the task started by Einstein
of rewriting all the laws of physics in
a way which is the same in every in
every frame of
[Music]
reference the preceding program is
copyrighted by Stanford University
please visit us at stanford.edu